<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>The Aranasaurus Nest</title>
		<description>Where @aranasaurus keeps his code and things</description>
		<link>http://aranasaurus.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://aranasaurus.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Week 1, Day 3</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Today I did more in-depth reading about the Lua-C interoperability and some coding, trying things out. My thoughts from day 2 still stand. Next up
will be making sure I can get that stuff working in my iOS project and then actually getting started on the C++ parts of the engine.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 02:39:12 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/27/week-1-day-3/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/27/week-1-day-3/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Week 1, Day 2</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Today I wanted to get it figured out where the line will be drawn as to which logic is written in C/C++ and what
gets done in Lua.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with reading the relevant chapters in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lua.org/pil&quot; title=&quot;Programming in Lua, AKA The Lua Bible&quot;&gt;Programming in Lua&lt;/a&gt;. From that I basically came to the
conclusion that the differences between making C functions callable from Lua vs executing Lua scripts from within
C are pretty negligible. So it becomes a matter of preference: Do I want the engine to be rooted in C/C++ with the
ability to delegate game logic implementation off to Lua? Or do I want the engine (and game logic) to be rooted in
Lua and the only C/C++ code being there to expose SDL, OpenGL, and any other C libraries I end up using for physics,
audio, animation, etc to Lua?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine these two options in a bit more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;engine-in-cc&quot;&gt;Engine in C/C++&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing the engine in C will of course mean more C code needing to be written by me, which I don’t particularly
enjoy. However, it’ll also mean that the hard part of the game(s) will be a bit more straight forward, as there
will only be one level of abstraction, and it’ll be more cleanly separated from the game logic. Basically meaning
I’ll be writing more C/C++ at first, but later on, when I’m doing mostly game-specific implementation, I’ll be in
Lua land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at how this might be modeled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cc-responsibilities&quot;&gt;C/C++ Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up window and OpenGL Context.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manage game loops.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maintains a list of game objects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Render loop uses properties on game objects to determine how to draw them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update loop calls an update function on game objects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Handle input and pass it off to game objects that care about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lua-responsibilities&quot;&gt;Lua Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game objects are defined as Lua tables with attributes for location and dimensions and possibly a texture name.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game objects have an update method which allows for updating their attributes every tick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically this set up boils down to the plumbing and architecture stuff being done in C/C++ and then there being a
communication layer between that scaffolding and all of the game objects, which are implemented in Lua.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After writing this all out I actually like this method a bit more than I did before doing so. Let’s see what that
process does on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;engine-in-lua&quot;&gt;Engine in Lua&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing the engine in Lua has the upside of everything being done in Lua and there being no extra layer between the
engine and entities. However, it does involve figuring out a way to get everything, everywhere bound to Lua, which
probably wouldn’t be too hard, but it just feels kinda dirty and like it will actually hinder dev speed a little
because it’ll be making the hard part of this project a bit more complicated without a lot of payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway let’s map it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cc-responsibilities-1&quot;&gt;C/C++ Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glue code which exposes SDL and OpenGL calls to lua.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lua-responsibilities-1&quot;&gt;Lua Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was less helpful than the C/C++ analysis, but I think I’ve come to my decision at any rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like I’ll be doing an engine based in C/C++ (which is another decision I’ll need to make very soon) with
game objects/entities implemented in Lua. Hopefully I’ll be able to get started on actually implementing some
functionality along these lines tonight after the kids go to bed and/or tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 19:21:16 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/25/week-1-day-2/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/25/week-1-day-2/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Week 1, Day 1</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Getting started on this week’s game on Friday night… The first week was already going to be a little funky
because I’d need to get a few pre-requisite things done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide on a framework and language&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get &lt;strong&gt;an&lt;/strong&gt; app built with said framework and language&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to templatize that app a little to make starting fresh each week easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few weeks are going to have a lot more engine development than later weeks as well, since I will
be starting from scratch (aside from what &lt;a href=&quot;http://libsdl.org&quot; title=&quot;SDL2&quot;&gt;SDL&lt;/a&gt; gives me, that is) in that regard. So I’m thinking the
first week is actually going to end up being 1.5 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight (and well into the wee hours of the morning) I did a bit of research and eliminated the &lt;a href=&quot;http://golang.org&quot; title=&quot;Go&quot;&gt;go-lang&lt;/a&gt; option
as it still can’t be built to iOS as far as I can tell. I’ve settled on SDL for sure, and got a templatizable
Xcode project started which is building to the Simulator. I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ciaranmccormack.com/sdl-2-0-on-ios-using-xcode-opengl-es-2-0-and-c-11/&quot; title=&quot;SDL 2 on iOS - Ciaran McCormack&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; quite helpful
in that endeavor. I started a &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/aranasaurus/game-a-week&quot;&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt; for the whole
challenge and put tonight’s progress in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I’ll need to do a bit more reading about doing Lua bindings, and experiment a bit with that and think
about how/if I want to design the engine with respect to that. I’d really much rather be writing game logic
in Lua than C++ for a myriad of reasons not the least of which being that Lua is just so much easier to write
quickly. Engine work will probably still be in C++ (or even C, for that matter), but I want to spend time really
thinking about the separation of concerns and where it makes sense to do the binding between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 03:54:15 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/25/week-1-day-1/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/25/week-1-day-1/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Game Dev Week</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;By day I’m a mobile developer working for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esri.com&quot;&gt;Esri&lt;/a&gt; at their &lt;a href=&quot;http://pdx.esri.com&quot;&gt;Portland R&amp;amp;D Center&lt;/a&gt;.
By night (and weekend), when not playing with my kids, I really enjoy making games, though. So recently I took a week off
from the day job to work on a game idea I’ve been rolling around for quite some time (while the kids are at school). I had
a prototype working but I wanted to give it my full attention for a week and see where I could get it in that time. I’ll
talk more about the details of the game in other posts, this one is more about the experience of said “Game Dev Week”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off the week trying to get the &lt;a href=&quot;http://getmoai.com&quot; title=&quot;MOAI SDK&quot;&gt;framework&lt;/a&gt; I had chosen to build and work. I really like the way Moai is
supposed to work: you set up a host for each platform you want to support and write a layer that takes the platform specific
stuff (like inputs) and feeds those things to Moai, then all of your game logic is the same for all platforms but you just
have to write the parts that differ. So I really like the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of Moai, but I couldn’t get it to work. I don’t want to
say that there’s anything wrong with Moai, per se, but their documentation leaves a lot to be desired and I just wasn’t dev
enough to get it working with my environment and requirements. I spent 2 days trying to do this and ended up giving up, so
that’s a significant portion of my week essentially wasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original prototype was done in &lt;a href=&quot;http://love2d.org&quot; title=&quot;Löve&quot;&gt;Löve&lt;/a&gt; which is really easy to set up and do rapid development with, however it
didn’t support mobile (officially) which was why I went with Moai. However I found this &lt;a href=&quot;http://love2d.org/forums/viewtopic.php?f=12&amp;amp;t=76985&quot; title=&quot;Löve for iOS&quot;&gt;branch&lt;/a&gt; of Löve which
touted some support for iOS (and it was branched off a branch with support for Android), so I grabbed that and decided to
use that for the rest of the week. I had to rewrite all of the stuff from my prototype, which was done with nothing but
gamepad controls support, plus it was a prototype, and that’s what you do with prototype code. By the end of the week I
had my mobile version with touch controls but not much else than my prototype had (in fact, slightly less), which was kind
of disappointing. And when I went to implement the next part of my game I realized that I was really going to end up needing
3D support, but only for the background. While this may be possible with Löve, it’s not what it’s designed for and it would
be a hack, even moreso than the mobile support (which is actually quite good), and I just didn’t want to go down that road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I came to the conclusion that what I’m really going to have to do is set up an OpenGL context of my own and basically do
what I wanted Moai to do, but on a smaller (more focused) scale. I plan on using &lt;a href=&quot;http://libsdl.org&quot; title=&quot;SDL 2&quot;&gt;SDL&lt;/a&gt; to handle windowing and input,
but that means using C++, which I don’t know very well. I’m considering doing lua bindings for the pieces of SDL that I need,
as I couldn’t get the SDL-lua bindings that I found to build on my machine and I didn’t want to go down that hole again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all that to say: I got the wind taken out of my sails for the current game idea and I need to take a step back and try
again with something smaller, which brings me to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-game-a-week&quot;&gt;A Game a Week&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/RamiIsmail/20140226/211807/Game_A_Week_Getting_Experienced_At_Failure.php&quot; title=&quot;A Game A Week - Gamasutra&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ramiismail.com&quot; title=&quot;Rami Ismail of Vlambeer&quot;&gt;Rami Ismail&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&quot;http://msminotaur.com/blog/?cat=4&quot; title=&quot;Game a Week&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://msminotaur.com&quot; title=&quot;@msminotaur&quot;&gt;Adriel Wallick&lt;/a&gt;), I’m going
to start building (and releasing) a game a week. The gist of the idea is that you build lots of &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; games and put them
out there for people to play. Get the experience of making something and finding out what sucks, what doesn’t, and why. But
doing so with tiny projects that you’re not sinking too much time/energy into. Another big part of this is that you don’t
touch the game again after the release, at least not as part of the Game a Week challenge. You can pick the game up later
and turn it into a full sized project, but each week is supposed to be something completely new. For my first few weeks I’m
going to keep it super duper simple, like Pong and Breakout clone simple, so that I can get an engine of sorts pieced together.
After I get a few of those out of the way and have some tools to work with I’ll start getting a little more adventurous with
my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the game each week I’ll be posting a post-mortem about it here, to log the process and provide access to the game!
It’s also possible that I’ll be posting about the week’s game throughout the week, depending on progress, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how long I’ll do the challenge, but my initial goal is going to be 8 weeks, starting next week. This post is the
first step in the process and I’ll probably get started on the Pong clone this week, even though it’ll be a short week, so I
can get the initial project set up stuff out of the way and be ready to go for reals next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I hope you’ll come back and try my games on this challenge, and send me some feedback on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/aranasaurus&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 09:42:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/23/game-dev-week/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://aranasaurus.com/2014/10/23/game-dev-week/</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
